<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynneth a lytell treatyse called the Lucydarye</title>
            <title>Elucidarius</title>
            <author>Honorius, of Autun, ca. 1080-ca. 1156.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1507</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72366</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13685.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125242</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900510</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900510</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173420</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72366)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173420)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2042:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynneth a lytell treatyse called the Lucydarye</title>
                  <title>Elucidarius</title>
                  <author>Honorius, of Autun, ca. 1080-ca. 1156.</author>
                  <author>Chertsey, Andrew.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1507]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated by Andrew Chertsey from a French version of the Lucidarius. Leaf E8 verso has de Worde's device, McKerrow 20--STC.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [aA]-dD⁶ eE.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173420:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173420:1"/>
            <p>¶Here begynneth a lytell treatyſe called the Lucydarye.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyſcyple.</p>
                  <p>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſter.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:173420:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S for to ſpeke of nobleſſe ſpyrytuall. It is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt grete nobleſſe that is / &amp; that man may haue. That is to haue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more his herte &amp; his affeccyon vnto his creature / to ſeche knowlege of hym &amp; of his ordynaunces / as wherfore he made the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles the man / the woman / maryage / paradyſe / hell / and where they ben / &amp; wherfore he wolde be borne of the vyrgyn Mary / &amp; the whiche ſygnyfyeth his dedes &amp; his werkes. And alſo of the Antechryſt &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deed bodyes and how a man ſholde confeſſe hym and to whome. Now enquyre we than of his thynges as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyſcyple dooth the whiche demaundeth of his may<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter / &amp; the mayſter anſwery<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vnto his demaundes as it foloweth.</p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:173420:2"/>
            <head>¶Here foloweth a lytell treatyſe Intytuled or na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med the Lucydarye good &amp; prouffytable for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well dyſpoſed perſone the whiche hath wyll &amp; affeccyon to knowe of nobleſſe ſpyrytuall.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of master and disciple</figDesc>
                  </figure>MAyſter tel me what thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge is god. My chylde he is a thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpyrytuall in the whiche is all dyg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyte &amp; all perfecci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on the whiche is knowynge al thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge all myghty / &amp; euermore dury<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge without ende and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out begy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge of an other. And alſo he ne may be meſured ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended of man ynough for to ſe hym ne his beautes ne may be no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred / ne his dygne puyſſaunce ne may be taken of ony entendement ſo moche is he grete. And alſo he is full of all bounty &amp; mercy. ¶Mayſter may he be but one onely god. My chylde / nay / For yf there we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re many goddes euery of theym ſholde be all puyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt &amp; than myght they make thynge contrary co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenable y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche is ayenſt nature dyuyne ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ne may be but one ſubſtaunce / &amp; one eſſence dyuyne the whiche is pryncypall cauſe effy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyent
<pb facs="tcp:173420:3"/>
of all thynges &amp; he is the ſouerayne good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the whiche euery herte deſyreth to come the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che entendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t humayne ne may comprehende ne ymagen. ¶Mayſter wherfore is god called fader. My chylde for the engendrement appertayneth pry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cypally vnto the fader more than vnto the moder / Wherfore man ſholde graunte vnto god the mooſt pryncypall partye. ¶Mayſter wherfore call we not the ſeconde perſone of the trynyte as well doughter as ſone. My chylde for as moche as the ſone is of more ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge nature / for he toke nature humayne in the fourme of man and not of woman. ¶Mayſter wherfore is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt called of the ſone &amp; the ſone were called moder. My chylde it is for that / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he procedeth &amp; dyſcendeth alſo pryncypally of the one as of the other. ¶Mayſter where was god befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re that he made the worlde. My chylde he was not in noo place corporell. For nothynge was but he all onely / but he was in hym ſelfe fader and ſone / &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly gooſt in one ſelfe eſſence. ¶Mayſter where is he now. My chylde god occupyeth no place. But his pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yſſaunce infynyte is ouer all / for he gouerneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges the whiche ben in the oryent / and thoſe the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ben in the occydent / &amp; generally all the worlde / and therfore a man ſayth that he is all tyme &amp; all thynges. ¶Mayſter knoweth god all thynges. My chylde / ye. for in lykewyſe as he is all puyſſaunt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he is all knowynge &amp; all ſeynge. ¶Mayſter in what maner made god the aungelles. My chylde he them made fayre &amp; ſhynynge and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out body and full of meruaylous bounte and ſaiges for to be his ſpecyall mynyſtres. ¶Mayſter how ſynned the aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the
<pb facs="tcp:173420:3"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of god. ¶Mayſter wherfore de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued the deuyll them. My chylde / by enuye for he was ful of ſorowe of that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they ſholde obtayne his place in paradyſe the whiche he had loſt by his pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. ¶Mayſter in what forme tempted the ennemy theym. My chylde / the deuyll appered vnto them in the forme of a ſerpent tellynge them that yf they ete of that fruyte they ſholde knowe as moche as god. ¶Mayſter wherfore ne created god the men confer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med in grace as the aungelles. My chylde god wolde that the men were ſemblable vnto hym as all thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges to take of hym / god wolde that all were borne of Adam. ¶Mayſter why had he not made them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myght not haue ſynned. My chylde to thende that they hadde the more of meryte. ¶Mayſter how had they engendred in paradyſe terreſtre. My chylde as thou ſholdeſt put thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one hande w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in thyn other w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ony delectacyon. ¶Mayſter how had theſe women chylded. My chylde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ony doloure &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out ordure. ¶Mayſter how had they be in paradyſe terreſtre. My chylde as a generacyon gone one after the other. ¶Mayſter where is paradyſe celeſtyall. My chylde it is in the tenth heuen the whiche is abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue all the other heuens and is cleped the heuyn Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial for as moche as it is more clere and more ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyll in ſubſtaunce / &amp; more fayre than all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other / In the whiche ben y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy men &amp; women of paradys en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braced w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the loue of our lorde. ¶Mayſter wherfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re made god man &amp; woman whan he knewe wel y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſholde treſpace his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement. My chylde it was for his pleaſure ſo to do for to ſhewe his infy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyte myght / &amp; vnto to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he were prayſed ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prayſynge
<pb facs="tcp:173420:4"/>
god and in demaundynge of his mercye of whome we ſholde take example / and by reaſon we ſholde do it more ſooner than the beeſtes that ne haue wytte ne vnderſtandynge / ſeynge the grete gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces that god vnto vs hath done the whiche ben ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vnto his ſemblaunce &amp; redemed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his precyous blode / and the whiche gyueth vnto vs too moche of good in this worlde. In ſuche wyſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the beeſtes plantes / trees / herbes / lande / &amp; ſee / planettes / &amp; ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / &amp; all other thynges ben made for to ſerue vnto the man vnto his prouffyte and vtylyte / and yet he hath lente vs the realme of paradyſe yf we wyll of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leeſt glorye ſurmounteth al the Ioyes of this worlde. By the whiche my chylde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man is we le to blame the whiche myſknoweth his creature the whiche ſo moche of grace to hym hath done ſeynge that the beeſtes the whiche ne haue wytte ne vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge / hym loue and thanke in demaundynge pyteouſly his ryght dygne mercy ¶Mayſter where was Adam create. My chylde he was create in bron &amp; after was put in to paradyſe terreſter. ¶Mayſter what thynge is in paradys terreſtre / and where is it My chylde it is a place delectable in the oryent ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mountaynes of egypt wherin ben trees of dyuers vertues / and of ſuche there are that who ſo eteth of them he ſhal neuer haue honger / and of other by na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture ſhall neuer dye. ¶Mayſter where was the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man created. My chylde ſhe was created in parady<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe terreſtre / but the man was create w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out for be put w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in in poſſeſſyon. ¶Mayſter wherfore ſynned the man &amp; the woman. My chylde by the decepcyon of the deuyll &amp; by theyr folyſſhe thynkynge treſpaſſed
<pb facs="tcp:173420:4"/>
&amp; honoured / for all thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges loue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god in theyr bey<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge &amp; alſo for they knowe well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ſhal be yet ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny perſones of more greter meryte &amp; holynes as yf they had not lytell ſynned / as ſaynt Iohan baptyſt &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> appoſtles &amp; dyſcyples of our lorde &amp; many other for as wytneſſeth the ſcrypture ryght happy is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may do yll / &amp; dothe it not whan he may. ¶Mayſter how longe abode Adam &amp; Eue in paradys terreſtre My chylde from the mornynge tyll vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houre of noone / for at the .iij. houre Adam put the names in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / &amp; about mydday they ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned / &amp; at none they were banyſſhed / &amp; at ſuche houre dyed Iheſu cryſte. Mayſter in to what place yede Adam wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was put out of paradys terreſtre. My chylde he yode in to ebron where he was create / &amp; there engendred he ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes &amp; doughters wherof we ben all comen where he wepte longe tyme his ſone Abell y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cayn kylled by enuye. ¶Mayſter ſyth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the deuyl te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; eue why were they ſo greuoſly puniſſhed. My chylde for that / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they myſtoke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of god for to obey to the ꝑſuacyons of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll / &amp; that they ne hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de them content w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god that ſo moche of grace vnto them had gyuen. By the whiche they ſynned in .iij. maners. That is to vnderſtande in pryde wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they myſtoken y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of god. And in couetyſe whan they were not content of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / that god vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had gyuen / &amp; in the ſynne of the mouthe in etynge the fruyte that god them had defended. ¶Mayſter whan y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he repented hym. &amp; alſo dyde grete penaunce wherfore was he not reſtablyſſhed after his deth in his fyrſt eſtate. My chylde for as moche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce was not ſuffycyent to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reparacyon of all thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173420:5"/>
he had put from paradyſe by his ſynne wherfore it was neceſſarye that the ſeconde perſone in trenyte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche is the blyſſed ſone of god made the reparacy on for hym / &amp; how be it that the blyſſed god is euer more mercyfull he is ryghtwyſe and rayſonable.</p>
               <p>¶Mayſter wherfore ſent not god an aungell for to by humayne lygnage. My chylde for as moche that yf the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell had redemed the man / he had ben ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gecte vnto the aungell &amp; god hath made the man to be in theſtate of aungelles / And alſo it was conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſyth the man had done the ſynne that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man hym repayred / &amp; alſo my chylde thou ſholdeſt kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we &amp; vnderſtonde that the blyſſed ſone of god in pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pre perſone wolde repayre the helthe &amp; ſynne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and to bere the penaunce and to ſuffre dethe and paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon ryght dolorous for hym and to humble hym to take our fragylyte &amp; nature in the wombe vyrgynal for to ſhewe the grete affeccyon &amp; the grete loue that he hath towarde vs the whiche he made vnto his ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blaunce. ¶Mayſter wherfore ne made god that an aungell toke nature humayne. My chylde for theſe cauſes that I haue now telled the / &amp; alſo for none aungell ne other creature ne had puyſſaunce to open paradyſe but god al onely / &amp; it was cloſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his treſpace / wherfore it was of neceſſyte that the ſonne of god were ſent downe here alowe for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme nature humayne / &amp; for to open hym paradyſe And knowe thou that he had in hym two natures. That is to vnderſtonde nature dyuyne / for he was and is very god / and nature humayne / for he was &amp; is very man / and for as moche vaynquyſſhed he the deuyll the whiche had vaynquyſſhed the man &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:173420:5"/>
paradys &amp; was of the lygne of Adam and dyde for hym penaunce. ¶Mayſter wherfore ne toke the fader &amp; the holy gooſt nature humayne as well as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſone. My chylde for that / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the ſone is the ſemblaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of the fader and graunteth vnto hym all thynges by the whiche it was a thynge conuenable that the ſone all onely drewe vnto hym the man for to dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we hym vnto his fader aboue in paradys.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyſcyple.</p>
                     <p>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſter</p>
                  </figure>MAyſter wherfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re wolde god be borne of the vyrgin Mary. My chylde god made the man in foure maners. The fyrſt was w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out man &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man as Adam. The .ij was of a man without woman as Eue. The iij. was of the man and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woman as we ben Now was to make the iiij. maner the whiche is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woman w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out man as is Iheſu cryſte. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other reaſon is ſuche for in lyke wyſe as the deth came in erthe by the wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man the whiche was Eue. Alſo the lyfe came in to the erthe by the woman. That is to knowe the vyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyn Mary the whiche vs hath borne the fruyte of ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe eternall. ¶Mayſter how chyldedſhe. My chylde ſhe chylded w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out payne and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out doloure &amp; abode entyer vyrgyn / &amp; pure / &amp; clene from al ſpotte before the chyldynge / at the chyldynge / &amp; after the chyldy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge
<pb facs="tcp:173420:6"/>
as the glaſſe thorowe the whiche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne paſſeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out makynge therin ony openynge. But for as moche as god wolde holde the ordre of nature he abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de nyne monethes in the wombe vyrgynall / &amp; he ne walked incontynent that he was borne. ¶Mayſter at what houre was he borne. My chylde he was bor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne at mydnyghte / and at that houre appered in the ſkye a ſterre moche fayre and clere that it was mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueylous to beholde / the ſonne was fayre as the gol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / &amp; peas and vnyte was thoroweout the worlde / &amp; obeyed vnto one onely prynce the whiche was na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med Ceſar / &amp; at that houre the dombe beeſtes ſpake &amp; ydolles of the ſarazyns &amp; paynyms fell to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe ¶Mayſter wherfore toke he the gyftes of the thre kynges. My chylde for in takynge the golde he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> he was kynge almyghty / &amp; by the enſence y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he was veray god. &amp; by the myrre very man / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge the whiche bare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> golde was called Baltha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſar / &amp; Iaſper bare the myrre / &amp; Melchyor bare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence. ¶Mayſter in how many maners ben our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes pardoned. My chylde they ben pardoned vs in. v. maners. Fyrſt by the ſacramentes of holy chyrche the whiche ben .vij. that is to knowe baptym / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macyon / confeſſyon / the ordre of preeſthode / the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the awter / the ſacrament of maryage / &amp; the vnccyon / but baptym is the fyrſt &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the whiche is mooſt clenly putteth oute the ſynnes / &amp; after bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tym / confyrmacyon &amp; confeſſyon ben the mooſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaryes. Secondely our ſynnes vnto vs ben pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by almeſdede. Thyrdely by oryſons / and by fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtynges. Fourthely by pardonynge vnto our enmy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. &amp; fyfthely by charyte. ¶Mayſter ben all our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:173420:6"/>
pardoned by baptym. My chylde ye / for by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ben as men vnto Ieſu cryſt in doynge hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this homage / &amp; we ben delyuered from the ſeruytude of ſynne. ¶Mayſter wherfore ben they baptyſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ben borne of them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ben baptyſed / &amp; alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren the whiche haue nothynge offended. My chylde yf ony paaſt were corrupte with venym all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche of it ſholde be made ſholde be venymous &amp; corrupte. And for as moche as our forne faders we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re corrupte by ſynne they &amp; all theyr lygnee were ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſſhed out of paradys terreſtre / &amp; vnto them were ſhytte the gate of paradys celeſtyall the whiche ne may be opened vnto the man / yf he ne be fyrſt bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſed as wytneſſeth the holy ſcrypture. &amp; how be it that the fader &amp; the moder ben baptyſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuffyceth not vnto the chylde for to be baptyſed / for whan a man hym baptyſeth / nature comune ne baptyſeth hym but all onely the perſone pertyculer / Wherfore it is of neceſſyte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ben al baptyſed in pertyculer ¶Mayſter wherfore ne named god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſed to be ſaued. My chylde it is not the defaute of god that all ne ben baptyſed / for he hath gyuen vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to euery man &amp; woman lyberall arbytre &amp; free wyll that to do. Alſo baptym ſholde be made of free wyll &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out conſtraynt for yf god conſtreyned the man to be baptyſed he had not his lyberall arbytre / and ſo all his baptym had no meryte. ¶Mayſter wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore eſpouſeth not man now his coſynes as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyente lawe. My chylde it is for to encreace loue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene ſtraungers / For thoſe the whiche ben of blode loueth eche other ynoughe more than theſe other / Wherfore it behoueth for to putte loue and charyte
<pb facs="tcp:173420:7"/>
where it is not / &amp; the other reaſon is ſuche. For the chyldren had two primites togyders as to be ſone and neuew wherfore for honeſte it was ordeyned to make maryage bytwene eſtraungers / but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde lawe men eſpouſed the women of lygnage &amp; it was for to multyplye &amp; to encreaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde. ¶Mayſter wherfore was Iheſu cryſte baptyſed. My chylde he was cyrconſyzed for to accomplyſſhe the olde lawe. and baptyſed for to begyn the new lawe &amp; for to ſhe we his grete humylyte in gyuynge vs example that we all ſholde be regenerate by baptym. ¶Mayſter Wherfore is baptym in water My chylde for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter is contrary vnto fyre / wherfore for to quenche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd fyre of ſynne we ben baptyſed in water. And in lykewyſe as the water waſſheth all ordures &amp; fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes. Alſo the baptym waſſheth all ſynnes / &amp; god theym eſtablyſſhed in water for as moche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is comune ouer all the worlde to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man fynde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoner mater of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none ne may excuſe hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ne coude fynde wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that he myght make hym to be baptyſed or that he myght haue. ¶Mayſter what worde ought a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeke in baptym. My chylde a man ought to ſay thus. I baptyſe the in the name of the fader / &amp; of the ſone &amp; of the holy gooſt amen. In puttynge thre tymes of water vpon the heed of hym that a man baptyſeth / &amp; ſo may they ſay in all languages / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it be in good beleue &amp; in good intenco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n &amp; other wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des the whiche ne ben of the neceſſyte of the ſayd ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament. of baptym. ¶Mayſter was it a thynge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable that god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fader gaue ſo noble thynge as is the ſone for to by agayne ſo caytyf a thynge as is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173420:7"/>
man. My chylde in that vs ſheweth god the fader the grete loue that he hath vnto creature humayne ¶Mayſter ſyth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god hath ſente downe here alowe his ſone by ſo grete charite &amp; for to redeme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> humay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes wherfore dyde men to hym ſo moche of payne. My chylde Iudas hym betrayed by couetyſe. Pyla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te hym condempned for drede to leſe his offyce / &amp; the Iewes hym put to dethe by enuye. ¶Mayſter wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore deyed Iheſu cryſte on the tree of the croſſe / My chylde for as Adam ſynned by the tree of lyf / Alſo god hym wolde bye agayne / by the tree of the croſſe and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholdeſt knowe that by the foure partyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe the whiche ſheweth all the worlde / it is agayn ſhewed vnto vs that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth of Iheſu cryſte was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fycyent for to bye not onely nature humayne / but al ſo all the vnyuerſal worlde yf it had be loſt ¶May<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter how longe abode Iheſu cryſte in the erthe deed / My chylde he there abode .xl. houres. And whan we ſay that he aroſe the thyrde day / &amp; that in thre da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes is not .xl. houres thou ſholdeſt vnderſtande that he dyed the fryday at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houre of noone / &amp;. all the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terday he was deed in the holy ſepulcre the whiche is the ſeconde day / and the ſonday after he aroſe ryght erly / &amp; for as moche as the courſe of nature is rene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed at mydnyght and the day / in takynge one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of the day for all the day entyer. ¶Mayſter why der yede the ſoule of Iheſu cryſte whan he was deed My chylde he yede in to glorye towarde god the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in yeldynge hym thankes and prayſynges in de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundynge hym the holy ſoules the whiche he had redemed by the meryte of his holy paſſyon / the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che thynge god hym graunted. Than opened y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le
<pb facs="tcp:173420:8"/>
of Iheſu cryſte the whiche was conioynte with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deite the gates of paradys the whiche had ben ſhytte by longe tyme vnto all humayne lygnage / &amp; the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terday about the houre of mydnyght he deſcended in to hel &amp; brake the gates &amp; yede to veſyte his good frendes. That is to vnderſtande the ſoules of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly auncyent faders the whiche gretely hym deſyred and them delyuered frome the pryſon of the lymbe withall the holy ſoules the whiche haue meryted pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>radys by theyr holy werkes / and this fayre compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mounted in to heuen and theym preſented vnto god the fader the whiche them receyued benyngnely and them putteth in to the realme of paradyſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> places and ſyeges that the curſed aungelles loſte by theyr pryde. And he delyuered not the ſoules of the dampned as Iudas / &amp; of the curſed ryche man dyues &amp; of many other / but them lefte in hel / in payne and in tourment with all the deuylles without gyuynge them ony comforte where they ben yet and ſhall be for euer. And on the ſondaye before the ſonne ryſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge retourned the ſoule vnto the body of Iheſus that laye in the ſepulcre / and roſe frome deth vnto lyfe / ¶Mayſter / wherfore aroſe not he as ſoone as he was deed. My chylde for a man had lytel preſumed that he had ben deed / &amp; he wolde begyn to renewe the worlde on the ſonday by his reſurreccyon. For at ſuche an houre all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde began to be. ¶Mayſter where was he after his reſurreccyon / fourty dayes be fore his aſcencyon. My chylde he was in paradys terreſter. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Helyas &amp; Enoch in enſtructynge them / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche was done as whan he appered. ¶Mayſter how many tymes appered he. My chylde / he appered
<pb facs="tcp:173420:8"/>
fyrſt vnto Ioſeph of barmathye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had buryed hym the whiche for ſoo doynge was put in pryſon. After vnto his moder / after to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blyſſed Mawdeleyne / af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .ij. pylgrymes comynge frome the holy ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pulcre / after vnto ſaynt Iames the whiche ne wolde ete tyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had ſeen hym. After vnto ſaynt Peter / after to the two pylgrymes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche went to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtel of maulx / after he appered vnto his dyſcyples y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gates ſhytte / after vnto ſaynt Thomas whan he put his hande in the ſyde of our lorde Iheſu cryſte / after vnto his dyſcyples in the ſee of Tyberyon / &amp; ſo my chylde y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholde vnderſtande y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lorde Iheſu cryſt appered .xii. tymes before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he aſcended in to heuen. ¶Mayſter who aſcended in to heuen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym. My chylde the ſoules of the blyſſed the whiche than by theyr merytes were ſaued / &amp; alſo grete multytude of aungelles of heuen the whiche hym accompanyed in ſyngy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge melodyouſly &amp; yeldynge thankes vnto god ¶Mayſter wherfore abode he .xl. dayes to mounte in to heuen after that he was ryſen. My chylde for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> that he gaue grete payne .xl. houres whan he abode in the erth vnto his frendes &amp; dyſcyples wherfore he wolde conforte them .xl. dayes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is one day for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry houre in tokenynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for payne he gyueth grete Ioye / &amp; alſo he dyde it for to conferme them in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly fayth / as ſaynt Thomas &amp; other / vnto whome he appered vyſybly. ¶Mayſter what is that to ſay / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſone is ſet on the ryght hande of his fader. My chylde it is to ſay that the humanyte is in glorye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the dyuynyte. ¶Mayſter in what maner &amp; fourme aſcended Iheſu cryſte in to heuen My chylde he ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in to heuen in ſuche fourme and maner as whan
<pb facs="tcp:173420:9"/>
he hym tranſfygured before ſome of his dyſcyples in the mountayne of Tabor that is to vnderſtande y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had the armes ſtretched &amp; lyfte vp in heyght / &amp; his face ſhynynge as the ſonne. And his veſtymen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes were whyte as ſnowe / &amp; a fayre and clere clowde deſcended from heuen / &amp; it cloſed rounde about hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſo mounted in to heuen in ſuche wyſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they loſte the ſyght corporall of hym. ¶Mayſter wherfore is the ſacrament of the awter made of breed &amp; of wyne My chylde for as the grayne of the corne hath ben beten and flayled &amp; had the ſede cloue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> In lykewyſe the precyous body of Iheſus was beten &amp; ſcourged / and hadde the ſyde opened / out of the whiche yſſued blode &amp; water / wherfore men put of water vnto the ſayd ſacrament. And as the wyne lepeth frome the grape by force of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wryngynge in the preſſoure. In lykewyſe the precyous blode of Iheſus lepte frome his precyous body on the preſſoure of the croſſe / and it was not eſtablyſſhed of the fleſſhe ne of the blode for a man may haue horroure to drynke blode &amp; to ete fleſſhe / but it was eſtablyſſhed of brede &amp; wyne / that is the mooſt comune refeccyon that is / and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the breed and the wyne ben y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt comune and the mooſt prouffytable for to nouryſſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body. In lykewyſe the ſacrament of the auter is the mooſt co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mune and the mooſte prouffytable refeccyon for to nouryſſhe the ſoule ¶Mayſter how ſhall we vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande that it is the body of Iheſu cryſte and his pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyous blode vnder the kynde of breed and of wyne. My chylde as the breed and the wyne that thou ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt &amp; drynkeſt conuerte them in to thyn owne body &amp; in to thyn owne blode. In lykewyſe the ſacrament
<pb facs="tcp:173420:9"/>
of the awter the brede and the wyne ſaynge the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly wordes by the wyll of god / alſo chaungeth them vnto the precyous body &amp; blode of Iheſu cryſte. and alſo he wolde do it for the grete loue that he hath in vs he wolde euermore be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs. And it is his po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to do / as of nothynge he hath made all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the whiche is a more grete thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. Than my chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſholdeſt beleue ſtedfaſtly &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out doubte for his pleaſure was it to inſtytute in ſuche wyſe. And how be it that thou ſeeſt it not corporally / for a body glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryfyed is inuyſyble y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte the more of meryte. For fayth is none other thynge but to beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſeeth not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>The mayſter</p>
                     <p>The dyſcyple.</p>
                  </figure>MAyſter / what ſay ye of them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che receyueth the ſayde ſacrament in mortall ſynne. My chylde / they crucyfye of newe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwete Iheſu cry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte &amp; hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receyueth vnto theyr damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ¶Mayſter the preeſt that is in mortall ſynne / may he ſacre &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynyſter the body &amp; bloode of Iheſu cryſte. My chylde ye / for the ſacramente ne empeyreth / ne amendeth
<pb facs="tcp:173420:10"/>
by the condycyon of the preeſt / as the ſonne whan y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhyneth vpon foule thynges &amp; ſtynkynge leſſeth not his clerete / but the preeſt it dooth vnto his damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacyon / &amp; yf he be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſynne it is vnto his ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon. ¶Mayſter how longe abydeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu cryſte in the wombe of hym the whiche hym recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uethe. My chylde he there abydeth as longe as the ſubſtaunce of the breed there may abyde vndegeſted and no more / but thou ſhalt vnderſtande that god there is &amp; alſo abydeth euermore w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ben in theſtate of grace. ¶Mayſter / whan many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſyngeth maſſe / the body of cryſte is it ouer all / My chylde / ye / For god is &amp; may be ouer all as thy ſoule the whiche is hole in euery partye of thy body ¶Mayſter ſholde a man hate the yll. My chylde a man ſholde hate theyr curſedneſſes &amp; folyes &amp; not to do yll as they done / but we ſholde loue our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / for we ben all the ſones of one fader &amp; of one mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der and bought &amp; redemed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one ſelfe blode / and yf they do the ony wronge thou ſholdeſt pardon them &amp; pray for theym vnto the example of Iheſu cryſte the whiche prayed for theym that hym crucyfyed &amp; put vnto the deth. For it is the werke mooſt meryto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous that we may do. ¶Mayſter wherfore haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yll ſo many of godes &amp; of proſperytees in this worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. My chylde there is not ſo yll in this worlde but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſomtyme dooth ſome good dede. And for as moche as man dyde neuer ony good dede but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed / ne neuer dyde yll but that it be punyſſhed And for this cauſe god them ſendeth of grete godes &amp; proſperytees in retrybucyon of theyr good dede. &amp; ſo vnto them gyueth puyſſaunce &amp; auctoryte vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173420:10"/>
good to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the good ben proued by theym / &amp; ſomtyme god ſendeth of trybulacyon vnto the ylle to thende that they amende them / &amp; yf they do it not neuertheles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall be in dymynuycion of theyr ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſholde haue &amp; ſuffre in hell. Or they ſhal haue encreaſynge of other grete goodes temporels but god gyueth of trybulacyons &amp; aduerſytees vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good for to proue them as vnto Iob / &amp; vnto Tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bye to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they dyſprayſed the vanytees of this worlde / &amp; that they ſholde not forgete theyr creature &amp; that by theyr merytes in takynge all in pacyence they may haue the glorye of paradyſe. &amp; ſomtyme god them gyueth of goodes to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be the more charytables &amp; that they augmenten in glory in paradys. The good dyeth ſomtyme anone to then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that they empeyre not for to auoyde the perylles &amp; temptacyons the whiche ben in this worlde / &amp; alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good lyueth ſomtyme longely for to encreaſe them in bounte / &amp; to thende that by theyr good example &amp; doctryne the yll may amende them / &amp; alſo the ylle dyeth anone ſomtyme for to make theſe other yll a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferde to thende that they amende them / &amp; ſomtyme the yll lyueth longely for to proue the good / and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for god taryeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſholde amende theym / &amp; ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſholde vnderſtand my chylde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the opynyon of ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me doctoures is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of god is ſo grete y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>freth euermore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man to dye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt eſtate &amp; purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may fynde hym. for god wyll not ne alſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth &amp; da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnacion of a man / but wylleth that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerte hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; lyue eternally in paradys / and how be it that many dyeth ſodey<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out hauy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſpace to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe them &amp; to do penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; ſatyſfacco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n
<pb facs="tcp:173420:11"/>
How be it vnto ſuche purpoſe may they dye &amp; in ſo grete contrycyon of herte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god theym taketh vnto mercy. ¶Mayſter ſhal the ryche &amp; the poore be egal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye guerdoned &amp; rewarded. My chylde of as moche as they be the more ſage &amp; the more dygne of as mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſhall they be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better rewarded whan they ſhal be good and whan that they ſhall mowe be yll of as moche ſhall they be the more greuouſly punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. ¶Mayſter may god doo yll. My chylde / nay / for how be it that he be all puyſſaunt / neuertheleſſe it is not entended that he may do thynges contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye vnto rayſon and that they ben Impoſſyble to be ¶Mayſter wherfore ſuffreth god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the beeſtes haue ſo moche of payne / &amp; alſo they haue not deſerued it My chylde it is ſomtyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by the ſynne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man the vengyaunce of god falleth vpon the beeſtes and vpon theſe other goodes to thende y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he amende him or for to proue hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as Iob. And alſo than beeſtes ben made to ſuſteyne and to nouryſſhe the man by the whiche they ben vnto his ſubgeccyon. And alſo for al thynges ſholde ſerue vnto that wherunto they be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ordeyned / as the brydge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche is made to paſſe / or to go ouer. In lykewyſe my chylde god it ſuffreth to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therby we take example / for ſyth that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beeſtes ſuffreth ſo moche of payne for theyr poorely fe corporall / we ſholde well more traucyle and take payne to gete the lyfe eternall of paradys in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che a man ſhall lyue eternally. ¶Mayſter knoweth god wheder a man ſhall be ſaued or dampned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he be borne. My chylde / yes / not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god it dooth in entencyon for to dampne hym / for god ne dampneth hym but the man dampneth hymſelf w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173420:11"/>
out ony conſtreynt but of his owne wyll the whiche is at his owne lyberall arbytre or fre wyll. As we ſe the boterflye the whiche of hym ſelf &amp; of his propre wyll hym brenneth in the candell. And how be it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſayd boterflye is ſomtyme ſcalded w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fyre of the candell in ſuche wyſe that often he falleth vnto the erthe / alſo he ryſeth agayne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt wyſe he can. &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all his power he putteth hym ſelfe agayne in the fyre of the candell all holly that he there abydeth / notwithſtandynge that he ſeeth well the daungere. Alſo done thoſe the whiche dampneth theym ſelfe / for how be it that they ſe and knowe the daunger y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therin is / &amp; alſo that they ben often ſcalded by try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulacyons &amp; aduerſytees to thende that they conuert them &amp; that by inſpyracyon dyuyne they haue ſome remors / how be it for that they ceaſe not tyll vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> that of theyr owne wyll &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ony co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraynt they put them ſo depe in the fyre that they there abyde &amp; ſhall neuer go forthe. And how be it that god wyl of ſymple wyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all men be ſaued &amp; hath one ſo grete a gyfte as the realme of paradys without ony mery<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / and by ſuche wyſe my chylde knowe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> that god hath made the man not to thende that he be damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned but to thende that by his holy operacyons in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>frynge pacyently trybulacyons &amp; aduerſytees / &amp; in reſyſtynge &amp; fyghtynge valyauntly ageynſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll / the worlde &amp; the fleſſhe / he may meryte to be ſaued. ¶Mayſter thoſe the whiche ben predeſtynate to be ſaued may they be ſaued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out deſeruynge it / &amp; to traueyle therfore. My chylde / nay / for god kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth well that by theyr merytes and traueyles they ſhall be ſaued. And in lykewyſe may a man ſay of
<pb facs="tcp:173420:12"/>
the dampned. ¶Mayſter ſyth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ben predeſtynate to be ſaued may they not be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned &amp; thoſe the whiche ſholde be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned may they be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued / what auayleth it elles ſo moche to trauayle, for to haue paradys or hell. My chylde yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be predeſty nate to be ſaued in the glory eternal y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ne ſholdeſt en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creaſe thy paynes in purgatorye / &amp; to leſſe thy glory in paradys by faute to do wele / &amp; yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>deſtynate to be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ne ſholdeſt therfore euermore lyue in ſynne / but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholdeſt euermore enforce the for to doo well / &amp; to do penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for to leſſe thy paynes in hell &amp; for as moche as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> knoweſt not wherunto y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtynate / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholde always thynke on the better ꝑtye / that is to vnderſtande y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god the hath made vnto his ſemblau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / &amp; hath bought the w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his precious blode for to ſaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> &amp; not to da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne the. Wherfore my chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholde euermore do good dedes &amp; to fle the yll &amp; knowe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> my chylde that god the hath gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wytte &amp; vnderſtandy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge reaſon &amp; fre wyll &amp; lyberall arbytre to choſe the good or y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ylle to thende that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haue not ony cauſe of Ignourau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or of Impuyſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ¶May<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter what ſay ye of them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche neuer hereth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes of god ne none they done. My chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the men ben made vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ymage &amp; vnto the ſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loue ſerue / &amp; drede and therfore yf they knowe not theyr creature in this worlde he ne ſhall knowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the other / ne yet by theyr Ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they ſhall not be excuſed but more ſooner accuſed / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce excuſeth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ¶Mayſter yf a chylde were nouryſſhed in a wood &amp; he had neuer herde ſpeke of the fayth of Iheſu cryſt ſhal he be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he dye in ſuche wyſe. My chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:173420:12"/>
it is a thynge to beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god maketh reuelacion vnto euery perſone of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faythe of Iheſu cryſte by te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chynge of man or by reuelacion dyuyne or otherwy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe / &amp; yf he go ayenſt the ſayd reuelacyon knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he ſhall be dampned. ¶Mayſter ben y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules made from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde: My chylde nay / but god the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> createth all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes &amp; them putteth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wombe of theyr moder y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to vnderſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vnto men at .xl. days after theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ¶Mayſter what auayleth vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. My chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde baptym. For in lykewyſe as by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tym all ſynnes ben ꝑdoned. In lykewyſe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſacrament of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyon all our ſynnes ben ꝑdo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned / for as moche as a man knowelegeth his detau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te before god or before his lyeutenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for god loueth more obedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſacrifice / for obedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is moder of all vertues. ¶Mayſter auayleth more penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce done by enioynynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſoure than penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce done by wyll. My chylde yf thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſour y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hath enioyned in penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce one pater nt<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all onely / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> leue it to ſay an hole ſauter y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſynneſt / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt not acquyte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> of thy penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / but yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſaydeſt the pt<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nt<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche to the was enioyned / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> leueſt to ſaye the ſawcer or other many fayre oryſons / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſayſt by ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple wyll y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt not ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne / but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt acquite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> of thy penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / for as I haue tolde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more better is obedyence done to our lorde than dooth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacryfyce. ¶Mayſter what auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trycyon at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poynt of deth. My chylde thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche abydeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to repent tyll vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houre of deth ben trechoures vnto our lorde as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trechoure &amp; yll payer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> promytteth to paye at a certayne terme but he wolde that the terme ſholde neuer come / and
<pb facs="tcp:173420:13"/>
for this mater &amp; cauſe he maketh a. M. trecheryes vnto his creature to thende that he ne pay hym ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne or neuer / &amp; of the other parte ſaynt Luke ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god is not well payed of hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche hym payeth of that thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ne may no lenger holde. How be it / it is wryten that at what houre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſynner ſhal declare his ſynne in grete repentaunce &amp; contrycyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it vnto hym ſhall be pardoned. But my chylde it is a ryght grete peryl to abyde hym to repent / for than a man is ſoo troubled that a man ne knoweth hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe ne none other / for as ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pſalmyſt. (Qm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt in morte q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> memor ſit tui: in i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferno au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t quis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitebitur tibi. That is to ſay / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deed man hath no remembraunce of god / &amp; that it is no tyme hym to repent &amp; to confeſſe his ſynne whan that a man is in hell for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence of god is gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Than my chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholde repent &amp; confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whan y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt tyme &amp; ſpace / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholdeſt not tarye tyll to morowe / for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> knoweſt not wheder y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte deye to mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe or ſooner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyſcyple.</p>
                     <p>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſter.</p>
                  </figure>MAyſter ſyth that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynne of pryde is pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by bapty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deyeth thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ben bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. My chylde the good deyeth to then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that they ben ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the trybu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacyon
<pb facs="tcp:173420:13"/>
of this worlde / &amp; they be crowned in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme of paradys / &amp; the ylle deyeth by theyr ſynnes to thende that they be put from the Ioyes &amp; delyces of this worlde / &amp; ben in grete doloure punyſſhed eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nally in hell. ¶Mayſter what noyeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſodeyn deth vnto the man. My chylde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> man the whiche dyeth ſodeynly / ſo that he be in theſtate of grace he gooth in to paradyſe or in to purgatory to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſſhe his penaunces / &amp; vnto hym the ſharpe deth is merytory<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous ageynſt his ſynnes venyalles &amp; vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dymynu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ycyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paynes of purgatory &amp; vnto the augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of paradys / &amp; yf he dye ſodeynly in mortall ſynne the ſodeyne dethe hym putteth in as moche as he is vnpourueyed &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out confeſſyon ne repentaunce taky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / than he is dampned eternal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly / &amp; by this &amp; for this cauſe my chylde thou ſholde be euermore redy for to deye in kepynge the frome ſynne / for thou knoweſt not whan ne of what deth y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte deye. ¶Mayſter what auayleth it a man to be buryed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrche yarde. My chylde yf he be in purgatorye he is the ſooner delyuered as well by the prayers of the chyrche as of his kynneſmen &amp; fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the whiche veſyteth his ſepulture in praye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge god for hym / And often it happeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the chyrcheyardes be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanctifyed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodyes of ſome ſayntes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; prayeth for them / wherof yf thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ben buryed ben ſaued they be ryȝt Ioyful whan theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyes ben w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bodyes of other ſayntes / but yf they ben da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned it prouffyteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good dedes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men there done for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne may helpe them ¶Mayſter what maner of lyfe is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt excellent &amp; beſt for to make his ſaluacyon. My chylde to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
<pb facs="tcp:173420:14"/>
a true affeccyon of true loue in our lorde in ſeruy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge hym &amp; honoury<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all his herte &amp; in eatynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt Iuſtly &amp; lawfully goten by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tra / uayle of thy body as wytneſſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pſalmyſt the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſayth. (Labores manuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tua<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>rum</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <abbr>qr</abbr> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducabis. &amp;c. That is to ſaye that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte be ryght happy yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> eate the laboure w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyn owne handes wherunto it is ſhewed the y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ne ſholdeſt vſe of the godes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che by the or by thyne be goten falſely / but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholde yelde theym yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> knoweſt vnto whome / &amp; to vſe of them the whiche ben Iuſtly &amp; lawfully goten.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>The mayſter</p>
                     <p>The dyſcyple.</p>
                  </figure>MAyſter he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche is in mortall ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne may he be longe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myttyng ſynne. My chylde naye / For as one gode dede drawes an other. In lyke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe one euyl dra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth another / for ſoo the deuyll ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man the whiche is in mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dooth of a beeſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ledeth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> top<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe wher it ſemeth hym beſt. ¶Mayſter whyder go y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben deed. My chylde the ſoules of the Innocentes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deyeth without baptym gooth vntoo the lymbe the
<pb facs="tcp:173420:14"/>
whiche is a chambre of hel where they ne haue Ioye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne heuynes / for they haue nothy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge meryted / but for as moche as they ne be purged from orygynal ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne by baptym they ben put from paradys / &amp; frome the vyſyon of god / &amp; the ſoules of them the whiche ben baptyſed the whiche dyeth in theſtate of Innocency gooth in to paradys all ryght. &amp; the ſoules of them the whiche deyeth in theſtate of grace &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne where yf they haue ſynned &amp; yf they haue done pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce ſuffycyent in this worlde gooth all ryght in to paradyſe / &amp; ben in glorye after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / that they haue meryted by theyr holy werkes / &amp; the ſoules of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche haue had contrycion &amp; dyſpleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theyr ſynnes &amp; ben retorned vnto god in cryenge hym mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy that they haue not acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſſhed theyr penaunces in this worlde gooth in to an other parte of hell na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med purgatory &amp; there they accomplyſſhe theyr pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces &amp; ben purged of theyr ſynnes / &amp; that done they go in to the glorye of paradys / And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules of them the whiche dyeth in one onely mortall ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne or many gooth in to the depnes of hell where they ben punyſſhed after theyr deſeruynge / &amp; the ſoules of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes &amp; of the meſcreauntes the whiche deyeth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſtate of Innocencye gone in to a parte of hell w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the other chyldren the whiche dyeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out baptym / but the ſoules of the other Iewes &amp; meſcreau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue wytte &amp; vnderſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge goth in to hell w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned ¶Mayſter in how lytel tyme ben y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules delyuerd fro purgatory. My chylde ſome there abydeth more longely than other after as they haue deſerued. for ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me ben delyuered at the ende of .vij. dayes / &amp; therfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re maketh a man the ſemell otherwyſe called the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>corn in maky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge prayers &amp; almeſdedes for theyr de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyueraunce
<pb facs="tcp:173420:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
/ for gretely vnto theym may puffyte the prayers &amp; almeſdedes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is done for them. Theſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ben delyuered at the ende of .xxx. dayes / &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is made the trentall. The other ben delyuered at the ende of one yere / &amp; therfore is made the yeres mynde / &amp; theſe other abydeth there by many yeres &amp; by longe tyme after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue deſerued / &amp; therfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re make men remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce euery yere of them / and whan they ben all purged &amp; that they ben delyuerd as by theyr penaunces acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſſhed / as by our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers &amp; orayſons / they go all ryght vnto the glory of paradys. ¶Mayſter in what place is paradys My chylde there ar .iij. maner of paradys. that is to wyte paradys celeſtyall / paradyſe terreſtre / &amp; paradys ſpy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytuall. Paradyſe celeſtyall is aboue all the heuens in the whiche is god &amp; all the ſayntes holy men and women as I haue ſayd before / paradys terreſtre is in the erthe towarde the oryent / &amp; paradys ſpyrytuall is anenſt god &amp; to loue hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perfytely &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ouer all In y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> paradys ben our good aungelles the whiche ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth &amp; loueth god. ¶Mayſter where is hell. My chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de there are .ij. maner of helles / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to wyte hell ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all &amp; hell corpall / hell ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>al is ouer all where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſed au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels ben in payne &amp; torment be it in erthe or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſee / &amp; this may be in many places / as we rede of a ſoule y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was tormented w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a flage of yſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a byſſhop delyuered by .xxx. maſſes / who was bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to be there longe tyme. Hell corpal is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myddle of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> carnell of an apple is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myddle of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apple &amp; is a grete caue blak &amp; darke in whiche ben iiij. ſtages y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other. At y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt ſtage is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place wherin were the holy ſoules of the holy faders au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by theyr holy lyfe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173420:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
haue meryced the realme of paradys the whiche our Lorde Iheſu cryſte delyuered whan he dyed on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree of the croſſe &amp; now there is none / For at that tyme were all delyuered. At the ſeconde ſtage is purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye wherin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules the whiche ſholde be ſaued goth to acconplyſſhe theyr penaunce the whiche they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not accomplyſſhed in this worlde in theyre lyfe In the thyrde ſtage ben the ſoules of the Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes the whiche deyeth without baptym. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .iiij ſtage the whiche is the mooſt lowe in depnes ben y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuylles &amp; the ſoules of the pore &amp; myſerable damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>The mayſter</p>
                     <p>The dyſcyple</p>
                  </figure>MAyſter what paynes haue they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in purgatorye.</p>
               <p>My chylde they ben tourmented with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre of hel moche more hoter than the fyre ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teryall of this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent worlde in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paryſon ayenſt a fyre paynted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a wall / &amp; they ben there bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de with chaynes of fyre al brennynge ſo ſper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kelynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man ne canne ſpeke it. In the whiche place ſome ben there more punyſſhed
<pb facs="tcp:173420:16"/>
than theſe other / &amp; there abyde more lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gely than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other after as they haue deſerued. ¶Mayſter what payne is there in hell. My chylde there are ſo many dyuers paynes &amp; tourmentes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is none enten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement humayne the whiche can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehende ne yma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gen as of fyre ſtynkynge &amp; ryght brennynge of to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / ſerpentes / dragons / &amp; of all foule &amp; cruel beſtes &amp; of deuylles enraged &amp; wode the whiche neuer ben wery for to bete &amp; tourment the poore &amp; myſerable da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned / but euermore ben for too begynne in ſuche wyſe that the leeſt payne of hell ſurmounteth all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paynes of this worlde / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one is more punyſſhed than the other after theyr deſert / &amp; at the day of Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gement theyr payne ſhall double for than they ſhall aryſe &amp; ſhall be dampned in body &amp; in ſoule. ¶May<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter what payne haue the ſoules of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Innocentes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche dyeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out baptym. My chylde they ne ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue payne / ne doloure / ne Ioye / ne gladnes. For they neuer dyde good nor euyll / by the whiche they haue not meryted to haue ony good / ne to haue ony euyll &amp; how be it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the place wherin they ben be dy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me &amp; derke / All be it there is nothynge the whiche theym greueth / &amp; whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye of Iugement ſhall come y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall ryſe they ſhall be of the aege that our lorde Iheſu cryſte was whan he dyed on the tre &amp; all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd chyldren not baptyſed ſhall be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god / &amp; than ſhall retorne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne in to theyr ſayd place w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out euer to haue Ioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne heuynes no more than y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt of that / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou haſt no wy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apertayneth vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byrdes &amp; not vn men / or as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt whan a kynge or ony grete pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce dyeth and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte not ſuccede his realme &amp; ſyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourye
<pb facs="tcp:173420:16"/>
for thou knoweſt well y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> arte not he the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſholde enheryte / Alſo they ne ſholde enheryte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gloryous realme of paradys for they ben exyled by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynne of Adam &amp; of Eue / of the whiche ſynne they haue not ben purged by baptyſm. ¶Mayſter thoſe of paradyſe ſe they thoſe of hell. My chylde ye / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnto them is a grete encreaſynge of glorye whan theyſe the paynes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue eſcaped wherof they thanke god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ceaſynge / &amp; alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dampned ſeeth the ſaued in paradys as we haue in the goſpell of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſed ryche man Dyues the whiche ſawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule of the poore lazare in the boſome of Abraham in pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>radys / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche thynge is to them a grete encreaſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of theyr doloure &amp; anguyſſhe whan they ſee the grete godes ſpyrytuall that they haue loſte by theyr ſynnes &amp; by theyr neclegence / &amp; after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of Iuge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment as the bodyes of the ſaued ſhall be <abbr>gloryfyed</abbr>
they ſhall ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned corporally / but the dampned ne may ſe them corporally. ¶Mayſter ben the ſaued wrothe of the payne of the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned. My chylde they that ben in paradys wolde well that thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ben in hell hadde ſoo well lyued whan they were in this worlde that by theyr holy werkes they hadde ben ſaued with theym. For without ceaſynge they praye for the humaynes lyuynge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in this preſente worlde / But ſythen that they by theyr curſed lyfe &amp; by theyr ſynnes they be dampned for euer theſe of paradyſe neyther ben heuy nor dyſpleaſaunt. For in paradyſe there is not of heuynes / nor of dyſpleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of ony thynge. But all Ioye / myrthe / and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe without ende. ¶Mayſter the auncyent taders ſuffred they ony maner of payne in the lymbe of hell
<pb facs="tcp:173420:17"/>
My chylde / nay / but all onely that they were holde in derkenes &amp; in captyuyte. And were put from the vyſyon of god and abode euermore theyr delyuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. ¶Mayſter what knowlege haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iuſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ben in paradys. My chylde they knowe the good &amp; theyr merytes &amp; of the curſed alſo / and the curſed knoweth wherfore they ben dampned / &amp; knoweth as we that thynge that they ſee &amp; fele. And thoſe of purgatorye ne knoweth nothynge of this worlde / yf if be not by reuelacyon of aungels the whiche them conforteth or of the ſayntes of paradyſe. Theſe of paradys ſheweth them whan they wyl / &amp; vnto who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me they wyll / but the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned ſhall neuer come forth of hell tyll vnto the day of Iugement that they ſhal come to take agayne theyr bodyes &amp; to here the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the ſouerayne Iuge / &amp; after they ſhall refor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne in to hell from whens they ſhall neuermore retor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne. And yf it happen ſomtyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſemeth vnto vs that they ſhewe theym it is but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll the whiche ſheweth hym vnto theyr ſemblaunce / yf it be not by the ſuffraunce of god that they ſhewe them ſomty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vnto ſome holy perſone as god it wyll by his my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racle as men ſayth of many / but it is not atte theyr wyll ne they be not eaſed of theyr paynes. For they here euermore theyr hell with them / and ſo they ben euermore in hell. ¶Mayſter how ſay ye of theſe wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men the whiche ſayth that they them ſe in the ayre of theſe feyryes / &amp; of theſe gobelyns the whiche the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> calleth elues and many other thynges. My chylde the women ben mooſt varyables &amp; more lyght of be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue than men / &amp; therfore was Eue tempted before Adam. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ennemy thought well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan he had
<pb facs="tcp:173420:17"/>
wonne her y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe ſholde helpe hym to wy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Adam / and therfore the deuyll ſhewed more ſoner his vyſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons vnto women than he dyde vnto men / how be it that ſome men of lytell fayth there ben often decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued / &amp; of as moche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome women ben of more ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght beleue of as moche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more the deuyll ſheweth of vyſyons vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theyr mynde for to drawe them frome the fayth of Iheſu cryſte / and thou ſholdeſt vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that theſe olde wytches the whiche ſayth that they go on the ſaterday fer frome theyr how<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes / or that they do or ſe thynges meruaylous y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ne doo nothynge / but by the grete fawte of fayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue &amp; by theyr folyſſhe beleue &amp; for as moche as they ben in ſynne / for they ben ydolatres and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out fayth the deuyll vnto them ſheweth thoſe folyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe vyſyons in theyr entendemente for the better to brynge them vnto his lyne / for in trouthe elles they remeue not frome theyr place noo more than dothe a ſtone / &amp; theyr vyſyons ben ſemblables vnto them of a man the whiche is dronke vnto whome it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the houſe torneth vnder his fete by the whiche he falleth / &amp; al the houſe ne the erthe remeue not. In lyke wyſe the deuyll them ſheweth theſe vyſyons in theyr entendemente / &amp; alſo the deuyll hym ſheweth in fourme &amp; ſemblaunce of ſome perſonage the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che they knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſholde be deed .xx. or .xxx. yeres paſt or in fourme &amp; ſemblaunce of ſome of theyr neygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boures / and ſhall ſpeke to theym famylyarly as it were themlſelfe to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they beleue hym the bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter / &amp; that he deceyue them the more lyghtly. but it is nothynge / but it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl hymſelf the whiche hym ſheweth vnto them in body fantaſtycall as for to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eyue
<pb facs="tcp:173420:18"/>
them / &amp; alſo maketh he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it vnto them ſemeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they go in to a medow grene ful of fayre floures vnto whome they make grete chere. But it is nothy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge / for they ne ben but ylluſyons made by the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye of nature y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he putteth in theyr entendement / &amp; it ſemeth them ſomtymes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they entre in to an hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe the gates ſhytte &amp; that they take the gaders of a chylde &amp; eteth them &amp; gooth in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> celler &amp; dry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keth as moche of the beſt / &amp; of that dede they go away w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde hath ony yll / &amp; that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyne is nothynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tonne the whiche is a thynge Impoſſyble / for all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſorcyers of the worlde ne all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuylles ne can make paſſe a ryght grete body hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne by a lytell clyft / ne entre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in a houſe / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he haue open paſſage for to entre / ne to drawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trayles fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of a chylde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out kyllynge or hur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge it / &amp; whan it ſhal be deed they can not areyſe it / ne they can not drawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyne of a ton<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> there be leſſe of one droppe / for they ben werkes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> all onely ben vnto the puyſſaunce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſouerayne crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure / Wherfore my chylde y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholde put no fayth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to theyr ſorceries &amp; deuyneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / for they ne ben but falſe Illuſyons made by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ennemy of nature y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tymes ſheweth ſome thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges for to come y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche he knoweth by ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iectures as I haue tolde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re in ſpekynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcyence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl / &amp; ſomtyme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll vnto them ſhall ſhewe a thefte in ſay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the trouthe to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better in hym / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the malfactoure be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more defamed / &amp; alſo ſhall ſay often trouthe to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoner beleued wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his falſe reuelacyon he ſhall accuſe ſome holy &amp; deuout perſonage / of whome he ne may be otherwy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe
<pb facs="tcp:173420:18"/>
auenged / &amp; for this cauſe a man ne ſholde beleue them / for they ne be but Illuſyons &amp; falſe vyſyons of the ennemy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ne dooth but lye for to decey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the man / &amp; alſo a man ne ſholde beleue ſuche peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll hath not ony puyſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſo be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god hym ſuffre / &amp; vnto the regarde of the feyryes the whiche men ſayth were wont to be in tymes paſt / they ne were men ne women naturalles but were deuylles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ſhewed themſelf vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme for they were paynyms / ydolatres &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out fayth / &amp; the ſayd feyryes chaunged them in to many fourmes / as of an hors / or of a dogge / or otherwyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche is Impoſſyble vnto nature but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl may wel ſhewe hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in many maners &amp; chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body wherin he ſhal be put &amp; in taky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ageyn an other of an other fourme a y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge thyn habyte in takynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> habyte of a relygyous man / or of a woman / but vnto the trouthe all the wytches of the worlde ne all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyls of hell ne can chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge one kynde in to an other / as a man in to a dogge / or a dogge in to an aſſe / for it is Impoſſyble vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to do / wherfore y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt wel thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe feyryes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in ſuche wyſe ſhewed them in dyuers fourmes &amp; ky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ne were men ne women / ne other thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge natural but were deuylles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in ſuche wyſe ſhewed them / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche put them in theyr ydolles &amp; ſpake &amp; ſayd ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me thynges for to come by ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iectures / as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Influences of the bodyes celeſtyalles / for otherwyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll hath no knowlege of thynges for to come &amp; by this meane y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd feyryes ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people were deſtenyed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one vnto good y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other to yll after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe of heuen &amp; of nature / as a chylde borne in ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:173420:19"/>
in houre &amp; at ſuche a cours / he was deſtenyed to be hanged or drowned / or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſholde be ryche or poore or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſholde wedde ſuche a woman / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges ben falſe / for the man hath in hymſelfe lyberall arbytre &amp; fre wyll to do good or ylle in ſuche wyſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf he wyll he ne ſhall do thynge wherfore he ſholde be hanged, ne yet put hym in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daunger to be drow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned / ne alſo he ſhall not mary a woman but yf he wyll &amp; ſo her deſtynacyons ſhall be falſe. By theſe reaſons a man ſholde put to no fayth / for as ſayth the pſalmyſte. (Dir ſapiens dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>abitur aſtris). That is to ſay / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wyſeman ſholde haue lordeſhyp abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the ſterres &amp; planettes / For he ſhall not gouerne hym after his ſenſualyte &amp; inclynacyon naturall / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut he ſholde gouerne hym wyſely by reaſon folowy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge the good &amp; eſchuynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ylle / for the wyll of man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſo free y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nothynge ne may make it vnfree / &amp; yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man ſholde do good or yll by force ageynſt his wyll he ne ſholde haue lyberall arbytre / &amp; ſo his lyfe ſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de haue noo meryte / the whiche thynge is falſe and ageynſt the fayth / Wherfore my chylde y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ne ſholde beleue it. It is alſo defended vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> payne of dethe and of dampnacyon eternall / and in regarde of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e wordes and of theſe ſperytes and elues / and alſo of many other vyſyons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſe by nyȝt they ben often deuylles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> put them in fourme of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me deed body in faynynge his voyce to tempte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſone of ſome thynge / for as ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pſalmyſt. (Spi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritus vadens et non rediens). y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule is departed from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body ſhe gooth vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e where ſhe hath deſerued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out euer toretome tyll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye of Iugement / yf it be not by grete ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſyte / 
<pb facs="tcp:173420:19"/>
&amp; grete myracle / as we rede of lazare &amp; of many other / but elues / gobelyns / &amp; helquins y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che men ſe by nyght / as men of armes trottynge on horſebacke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grete aſſembles / they ben deuylles the whiche ben amonge vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche ſheweth theym in ſuche a fourme and in many other fourmes as of a dogge / of an horſe / of a tree / or of a ſtone / &amp; in ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny other fourmes for to tempte the man of ſome vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / &amp; for to make hym erre in the fayth / &amp; ſomtymes theſe deuylles cometh vnto the ſtables &amp; fyndeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horſe &amp; tourneth all that the whiche was aboue <abbr>vnd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth</abbr>
by deryſyon of the man &amp; for to tempte hym / and ſomtyme they vnbynde the lytell thyldren and them caſteth from the cradell for to make the fader and the moder wrothe &amp; often kyll the chyldren wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god it ſuffreth / for the ſynne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fader / or of the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der / or for to proue them as he dyde Iob whan he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fred that the deuyll hym dyde ſoo many of ylles / &amp; of tourmentes for to preue hym in his grete pacye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> permyſſyon of god they haue no pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yſſaunce / but ben as the hange man the whiche w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the byddynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iuge ne may hange ne bete ony euyll doer. wherfore my chylde thou ſholdeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnto god &amp; vnto the ſayntes &amp; to lyue holyly as ſayth the pſalmyſt. (Non timebis amore noctur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>no. That is to ſay thou ſhalte not drede of choſe fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſhe vyſyons by nyght. For they ne ben but Illuſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons made by the ennemye as it is ſayd. ¶Mayſter may the ennemy be conſtrayned to come by wordes or by ſygnes. My chylde nay / yf he ne wyll / but they ben the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaunces y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben of his ſecte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche in ſaynge ſome wordes / or in maky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge
<pb facs="tcp:173420:20"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> or cara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es thyder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>keth that / that he demaundeth / to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he them holde the better in his lyne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>The mayſter</p>
                     <p>The dyſcyple.</p>
                  </figure>¶Mayſter what ſay ye of theſe dre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes My chylde y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholde take no he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de vnto them for they ne be but vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſome thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges on y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche a man hath thouȝt or ſeen before wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / &amp; a man dre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth often of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche is ſembla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble vnto his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexyon. ¶May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter how knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝓphetes tho day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they ſawe by dreme. My ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was not by dremes all onely / but it was by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reuelacyon of god / for w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the vyſyon they had an y<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>magynacyon &amp; beleue eſpecyal in the bounte of our lorde that / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge that they had ſeen in ſlepynge came. ¶Mayſter ſyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god dyſcended in erthe for to ſaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynners wherfore ben they dampned. My chylde there is not ſo grete a ſynner in the worlde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> &amp; yf he reknowelege his ſynne &amp; crye god mercy w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good herte but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he be perdoned by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meryte of the doth &amp; paſſyon of Iheſu cryſte / but thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyl not
<pb facs="tcp:173420:20"/>
knowlege theyr ſynne but ben obſtynate tyl vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dethe / know y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> that they ben dampned eternally for god ne ſaueth the ſynner the whiche wyll not ſaue hymſelfe / &amp; alſo paradyſe is not deſerued by ſynne but it is loſt. ¶Mayſter ſyth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god deyed for our ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes wherfore ben we baptyſed. My chylde for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tym is the homage y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we owe vnto our lorde Iheſu cryſte by the whiche all our ſynnes ben pardoned &amp; in ſuche wyſe ordeyned he it as telleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel that ſayth thus. (Quicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> baptiſatꝰ fuerit. That is to ſay / who ſo ſhall be baptyſed ſhall be ſaued / &amp; he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is not ſhall be dampned. ¶Mayſter how many per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones ſhall be ſaued. My chylde there ſhall be as ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſaued as there fell of the curſed aungelles of pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>radys by theyr pryde / for the men &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> women ben made for to be in theyr place / &amp; for that cauſe is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ennemy ſo enuyous ayenſt man. ¶Mayſter frome whens came the fyrſt ydolatres My chylde they we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re fyrſt founde in abell the whiche is now called ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bylon the grete &amp; there ſhall y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> anthecryſt be borne &amp; there was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> toure with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gyauntes the whiche is of xl. ſtages. There regned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt kynge of this worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the whiche men called Neron the whiche cauſed to be made an ymage of Appolyn / &amp; <abbr>commaunded</abbr>
all thoſe of his realme that they ſholde do hym ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafyce &amp; worſhyppe hym &amp; in lykewyſe dyde they the whiche came after hym in ſuche wyſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me grete prynces were deed theyr ſucceſſoures cauſed to make of ymages meruaylouſly ryche in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of theyr <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>deſeſſoures / &amp; made theyr ſubgettes to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; to do ſacryfice &amp; were called ydolles in to whome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll entred &amp; ſpake &amp; tolde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many
<pb facs="tcp:173420:21"/>
of abuſyons &amp; ſo dyde they of grece vnto theyr kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge / &amp; they of rome vnto Romulus as men fy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de by the wryty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges &amp; au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyent cronycles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of master and disciple</figDesc>
                  </figure>¶Mayſter wher for ne made god that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne ſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ete but one ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a weke My chylde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honger is one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſuffre by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; ſo we haue eueri day honger: and thyrſte / colde / &amp; heet / &amp; many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſyons to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle alway for to thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke on oure nedes &amp; of oure neyghboures / to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by our trauayle &amp; labour contynuall we haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more of meryte / for yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man had not of neceſſyte he ſholde haue noo care to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle / but he ſholde be euermore in ſlouthe / &amp; ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de not knowe what good were worthe / and alſo he ſholde myſknowe his creatoure: And how be it that the grete lordes and gentylmen and other ryche tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uayleth not corporally / All be it they trauayle ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytually euermore. That is to vnderſtande in theyr vnderſtandynge and wyll in hauynge euermore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre to gete / for he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt hath &amp; more wolde haue
<pb facs="tcp:173420:21"/>
of as muche is it the more grete / &amp; whan y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> confeſſed all thy ſynnes wherof thou remembred y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thou ſholde crye god mercy w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good herte in grete contrycyon &amp; dyſpleaſaunce / and in demaundynge of thy confeſſoure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyeutenaunt of god abſolucyon &amp; penaunce / the whiche y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholde accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plyſſhe entyerle vnto thy power in grete reuerence. &amp; thou ſholde kepe the frome ſynne as moche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſt / ſpecyally durynge the tyme of thy penaunce ¶Mayſter vnto whome ſholde a man confeſſe hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. My chylde vnto a preeſt dyſcrete &amp; wyſe the whiche knoweth what it is of ſynne / &amp; who hath it not / &amp; who that can dyſcerne bytwene the ſynne mortal &amp; denyall / for who ſo confeſſeth hym vnto preeſt not knowynge &amp; Ignouraunt putteth his ſoule in grete te aduenture for ryght often y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confeſſyon is nothyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge worthe. ¶Mayſter may a man confeſſe hym to ony other but vnto his curate. My chylde yf thou be in a ſtraunge countree y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt confeſſe the vnto hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wyll / And yf thou be in thy paryſſhe &amp; thou wyll not confeſſe the vnto thy curate the whiche is Ignouraunt / or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy ſynne touche his perſone / or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhewe thy confeſſyon wherby there myght come ony ſclaunder / or by many other reaſons thou ſhold demaunde lycence / &amp; yf he wyll not gyue it the thou may take an other of thyn owne auctoryte. But yf thou confeſſe the vnto them the whiche haue the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer &amp; the puyſſaunce of the byſſhop / or of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as be many grete clerkes and grete prechoures / thou may do it without lyſence of thy curate / ſoo that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be confeſſed vnto thy curate one tyme in the yere / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> may confeſſe the elles where as often as thou wyll
<pb facs="tcp:173420:22"/>
your lycence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyſcyple.</p>
                     <p>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſter.</p>
                  </figure>MAyſter how &amp; fro whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhall the Anthecryſt come. My chylde he ſhall be borne in ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bylon of a <abbr>curſed</abbr>
man &amp; of a curſed woman the whiche ſhall be of the lyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of Dam / &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wombe of his mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der he ſhal be ful of the curſed ſperyte &amp; ſhall be nouryſſhed &amp; confermed in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntementes and ſhal be emperoure of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / &amp; ſhall put the people vnder hym in foure ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. That is to vnderſtonde the prynces &amp; other ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che / &amp; couetous by gyftes / for he ſhall haue by his en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chauntementes all the treſoures hydde in the erthe. The poore by grete drede &amp; rygoure of Iuſtyce / for he ſhall make them greuouſly to be martred. The clergye by connynge wherof he ſhall be full / For he ſhall conne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vij artes &amp; al the other ſcryptures. &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuout perſones by tokens &amp; by myracles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall be meruaylous. For he ſhall make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre to dyſcende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall brenne his enmyes before hym / &amp; alſo he ſhall make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deed men to aryſe / not truely / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll ſhall entre in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodyes of ſome da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned &amp; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uylles ſhall bere them / &amp; anone make them to ſpeke by his enchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tement &amp; to walke as yf they were a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue / &amp; ſhall reedyfye <abbr>Ihrlm</abbr> &amp; there he ſhall make
<pb facs="tcp:173420:22"/>
mooſt hath in thynkynge / &amp; ſoo my chylde none ne may lyue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out payne and trauayle / but euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath moche to do in his ryght.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>The mayſter</p>
                     <p>The dyſcyple.</p>
                  </figure>MAyſter what be tokeneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryes and cermoni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make vnto the chyrche. My chylde they ſhewe vs good ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample / &amp; we fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure the olde teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment &amp; the newe &amp; our lorde Iheſu cryſte is loued in the chyrche at the houres of maty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for at ſuche houre he was taken of the falſe Iewes &amp; ledde vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grete preeſtes of the lawe / as it is wryten in the houres of the croſſe / at pryme / for at ſuche houre he was ledde &amp; brought before Pylate where he was falſely accu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed &amp; vylanouſly ſcourged at the thyrde / for at ſuche houre he was crowned with thorne &amp; clothed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple by deryſyon &amp; was cladde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a whyte robe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of Herode by grete mockerye / at the ſexte / for at ſuche houre he was hanged &amp; nayled on the croſſe at noone / for at ſuche houre he dyed on the tree of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe / at euenſonge tyme / for at ſuche houre his pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyous
<pb facs="tcp:173420:23"/>
body was taken downe from the croſſe &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> precyous oyntementes / &amp; at co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyne / for at ſuche houre he was buryed / &amp; thou ſhalte vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonde that in the maſſe vnto vs is fygured y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth &amp; paſſyon of Iheſu cryſt by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aulbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyte robe wher with he was cladde / &amp; by the chaſuble the robe of purple &amp; men ſay the pyſtle on the ryght hande / for it is the token of the good lyfe the whiche ledeth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the ryght hande of paradys / &amp; men rede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell on the lyfte hande / for by the lyft hande vnto vs is ſygnyfyed ſynne / for the goſpell is the mooſt ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge &amp; of mooſte grete vertue / &amp; therfore it is put on the lyfte hande for to defende vs ayenſt ſynne / for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſholde euermore put the mooſt ſtrongeſt ayenſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye from whens cometh the ſtrokes / &amp; the ymages well hydden in ſhewynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god &amp; the ſayntes of pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>radys haue abhomynacyon of our ſynnes &amp; to ſpeke well there ne is cermonye but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhewe vnto vs ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me grete myſtere. ¶Mayſter how ſholde a man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe hym. My chylde y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholde fyrſt examyn thy con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcyence in recordynge the places where y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte ben &amp; how thou there haſt lyued / for there ne is thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that better dooth to thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke of ſynnes as to recorde the pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces where a man hath be / &amp; in ſo doynge y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholde ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amyn thy conſcyence. Fyrſt of thy fyue wyttes natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ralles. That is to knowe of thyn eyen / of eeres / of handes / of atouchynges / of the mouthe / of the noſe &amp; of al thyn herte. Secondely alſo of the vij. mortal ſynnes / &amp; of theyr braunches the whiche ben .vij / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to vnderſtande / pryde / couetyſe / enuye / yre / gloto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lechery / &amp; ſlouth. Thyrdely of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xij. artycles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben conteyned in the crede. Fourthly of the .x
<pb facs="tcp:173420:23"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of the lawe the whiche our lorde gaue vnto Moyſes. Fyfthly of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vij werkes of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſſhe them whan y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt well doo it. Sextely of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vij. ſacramentes of the holy chyrche yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ne haſt had in them perfyte beleue / And ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thly of the .vij. cardynall vertues / yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> hath had them in the &amp; kepte as thou arte bounde to do. &amp; that done y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholde go to confeſſe the w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grete humylyte and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trycyon &amp; dyſpleaſaunt of thy ſynnes / in hauynge ferme purpoſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte them noo more / for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe thou repenteſt the not. And whan thou ſhalte be before thy confeſſoure in grete humylyte confeſſe vnto hym all thy ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes entyerly / and clerely that he vnderſtande it in tellynge hym all the fourme &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner how &amp; wherfore thou haſt commytted theym / &amp; alſo thou ſholde tell the tyme &amp; the place yf thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre it for yf thou ſynne the holy dayes / thou ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſt more greuouſly than on the werkynge dayes &amp; yf thou ſynne in place halowed thou ſynneſt more than in an other place / &amp; in confeſſynge the y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de holde the ordre of confeſſyon in tellynge by ordre thy ſynnes as thou haſt them recorded before to then<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de that thou forgete not / and ſo thou ſholde tell all vnto thy confeſſoure / for yf thou leue one vnto thy wyttynge for ſhame or otherwyſe thy confeſſyon is none / for it is not entyere / Ne alſo thou ne ſholde de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parte thy confeſſyon in tellynge the one halfe vnto one confeſſoure / and the other halfe vnto an other confeſſoure / For alſo it is not entyer and hole / aad it is nothynge worthe / but thou ſholdeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe and ſhryue the entyerly vnto one confeſſoure of all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre / How be it yf after thy confeſſyon
<pb facs="tcp:173420:24"/>
thou remembreſt ſome thynge thou mayſt well con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe the vnto an other / but yet thou ſhalt do better to retorne vnto the fyrſt yf thou mayſt. Alſo my chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholde confeſſe the cyrcumſtaunces of thy ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes in tellynge that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche hath moeued the vnto ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / the fourme &amp; the maner that thou haſt holden in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myttynge thy ſynne / &amp; the yll the whiche cometh vnto an other &amp; vnto thy ſelfe. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholdeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the of yll examples that thou haſte gyuen vnto an other by thy ſynne and alſo thou ſhalte confeſſe the of wyll &amp; conſentynge that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt had / &amp; of the payne that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte taken for to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte it / for who ſo conſenteth to ſynne all onely yf it be mortall / he ſynneth mortally as wytneſſeth the holy goſpell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſter</p>
                     <p>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyſcyple</p>
                  </figure>Alſo my chylde y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de tel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dignite &amp; proxi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myte of the perſone w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whome thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myttes the ſynne as yf the were a vyrgyn / or a relygyous woman / or maryed or thy kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſ woman / or a comy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> woman without na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge her otherwyſe. For in thy confeſſyon thou ſholdeſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the of the ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of an other ne dyffame her / but thou ſholde all onely tell her eſtate for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the gretenes of thy ſynne / for of aſmoche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſone is dygne in whome the ſynne is commytted
<pb facs="tcp:173420:24"/>
the begynnynge of the worlde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al the deuyls. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is done oure lorde Iheſu cryſte &amp; all his holy aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles &amp; archau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels ſhall mounte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the good in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory eternall af paradys. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſed ſo ſhal deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cende in to hell w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the deuylles from whens they ſhall neuer come ne departe / but ſhall be euermore in payne / doloure / &amp; heuynes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre of hell perdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably. ¶Mayſter whiche ben thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall be damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned. My chylde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall be the Iewes / &amp; myſbeleuers &amp; the curſed cryſtyens that ſhall deye in mortal ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne without repentaunce. And men ſhall ſe clerely at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye of Iugement y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſcyence the one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other / wherby euery man ſhall gyue Iugement of hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe &amp; in this maner ſhall be knowen all the good dedes &amp; the yll. For a man dyde neuer ony ylle ne ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne be it neuer ſo ſecrete / but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> than it ſhall be clerely ſeen &amp; ſhewed openly before god &amp; before all the worlde. ¶Mayſter what ben y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ioyes of paradys. My chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de they ben ſo ryght grete y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man ne can tell them. For the ſaued ſhall ſe god face to face &amp; ſhal knowe all thynges as the aungelles. The bodyes of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſhall be clere and ſhynynge as the ſonne / they ſhall be incontynent where they wyl be as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thought the whiche incontynent is borne thyder where it ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. They ſhall haue no ſhame to be all naked the one afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other for they ſhall be all cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed fro ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne &amp; ſhall be ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fermed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of our lorde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may neuer ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne more ne haue ony euyl thouȝt / they ſhal ne haue ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger ne thyrſt / for they ne ne ſhal be more ſubgectes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> influe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> planet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes meanely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alſo maketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> degeſtyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body humayne but ſhallbe there aboue incorruptybles &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:173420:25"/>
and fedde of the grace of god / they canne not ceaſe to yelde graces &amp; prayſynges vn to god of the grete mercy that he vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath done. And to ſpeke ſhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely the Ioyes of paradys ben ſo grete that there ne is entendement the whiche them can comprehende / For yf all the goodes / and all the Ioyes and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes the whiche ben / was / and ſhall be in the wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were all to gyders y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſholde be nothynge vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paryſon of the leeſt glory of paradys. For all the Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yes of this worlde ben tranſytoryes / and alſo paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth as ſmoke. But the Ioyes of paradys ben per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuelles and without ende.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of master and disciple</figDesc>
                  </figure>¶Mayſter how many ordres of aungelles ben in ꝑadys. My chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de there be nyne The fyrſt ordre is called the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre of ſeraphy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the whiche is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt hygheſt / The ſeconde of the Cherubyns. The thyrde is of the thrones / The fourthe of the puyſſaunces The fyfth is of the prynces. The ſyxte of the ſeygnouryes: The ſeuenth of the
<pb facs="tcp:173420:25"/>
vertus. The eyght of the .ix. ordres as lordes aboue theyr ſeruauntes archaungels. And the nynth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aungelles the whiche is mooſt lowe. and al the ſayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes holy men &amp; women of paradys ben aboue them ¶Mayſter haue we euery of vs his good au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell the whiche kepeth vs: My chylde euery one hath his go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de aungell the whiche hym defendeth from the ylle and ſtyreth hym to do wele / and ſoo hadde our lorde Iheſu cryſte of good aungelles for to mynyſter vnto hym. And the Anthecryſt ſhall haue one to kepe hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from doynge of ſo moche yll as he may well. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles ben of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſte &amp; mooſt lowe ordre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led proprely the ordre of au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelles as I haue now tol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the. ¶Mayſter wherfore loſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mone ſomtyme his clereneſſe. My chylde the mone hath none other lyght but that / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſonne vnto her gyueth / ſo it hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peneth often that the erthe is founde bytwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the mone in ſuche wyſe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne ne may gyue her clerenes / and than ſhe is all blacke / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe ſhadoweth her But whan the erthe is not dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectely betwene them / but ſome parte all onely than is ſhe clere in as moche as the ſonne mayſe her / &amp; whan the erthe is nothynge betwene them than is ſhe clere / for there is nothynge bytwene theym. And for that cauſe hath the mone euer the backe towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the ſonne. ¶Mayſter what thynge is the bowe of heuen the whiche we ſe in the ayre. My chylde they ben the beames of the ſonne the whiche medle them in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater of the mone y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche is thycke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche taketh foure coloures y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche ben dyſpoſed to recey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue many &amp; dyuers coloures after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of herbes &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place where they growe. ¶Mayſter fro whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:173420:26"/>
cometh the wyndes / thondres / froſtes / ſnowes / ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / dewes / &amp; ſuche ſemblable thynge. My chylde al theſe thynges cometh of ſome vapoures the whiche aryſeth frome the erthe in heyght by the vertue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne / of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche ſome ben drye / &amp; the other moyſt &amp; whan ſuche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche ben lyft vp tyll vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne regyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche is ryght colde they ben made thycke &amp; begyn to droppe / &amp; frome thens co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the rayne. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> colde is gretely deſtray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge aboue ſo they aſſemble &amp; congeleth / &amp; frome thens cometh the hayle / &amp; whan theſe droppes fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth here alowe / &amp; fyndeth this bace region of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayre colde, as in wynter they alſo congele meanely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the whiche is colde &amp; frome thens cometh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes / and this dewe is made of the ſelfe vapoures / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche whan they dyſcende vpon the erthe / &amp; there fyndeth colde they conuerte them in to water. But whan theſe vapoures ben drye &amp; lyght they aryſe vp more hye vnto the thyrde regyon of the ayre the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is hote / for it toucheth the regyon of the fyre in ſuche wyſe whan the vapoures drye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe clerkes calleth exalacyons paſſeth in the ayre &amp; meteth the one with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other / the mooſt ſtrongeſt cadereth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte weykeſt by the vertue of the ſonne &amp; of the mone / &amp; frome thens cometh the wyndes / &amp; whan theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>alacyons paſſeth in mountynge by the meane regy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayre the whiche is ryght colde they meddle them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the cloude &amp; cloſeth them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> colde: &amp; the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſtryketh bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gely bytwene theſe clou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des in ſuche wyſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe exalacyons hote y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloudes wyl go forth / but they ne may for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloude is colde &amp; thycke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche holdeth the
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:173420:26"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
